Assignment 5: Begin a transaction, perform a series of INSERTs into 'orders', setting a SAVEPOINT after each, 
rollback to the second SAVEPOINT, and COMMIT the overall transaction.

Suppose we have an 'orders' table with columns 'order_id', 'customer_id', and 'order_date'. We'll begin a transaction
, perform a series of INSERTs into the 'orders' table, set a SAVEPOINT after each INSERT, rollback to the second SAVEPOINT, 
and finally, commit the overall transaction.

Here's the example SQL code:
-- Begin the transaction
BEGIN TRANSACTION;

-- First INSERT
INSERT INTO orders (order_id, customer_id, order_date) VALUES (1, 101, '2024-05-15');
SAVEPOINT first_savepoint;

-- Second INSERT
INSERT INTO orders (order_id, customer_id, order_date) VALUES (2, 102, '2024-05-16');
SAVEPOINT second_savepoint;

-- Third INSERT
INSERT INTO orders (order_id, customer_id, order_date) VALUES (3, 103, '2024-05-17');
SAVEPOINT third_savepoint;

-- Rollback to the second SAVEPOINT
ROLLBACK TO SAVEPOINT second_savepoint;

-- Commit the overall transaction
COMMIT;

In this example:

1)We begin a transaction using the BEGIN TRANSACTION statement.
2)Three INSERT statements add rows to the 'orders' table, with each row representing an order.
3)After each INSERT, we set a SAVEPOINT using the SAVEPOINT statement.
4)We then rollback to the second SAVEPOINT using the ROLLBACK TO SAVEPOINT statement. This means any changes made
 after the second SAVEPOINT will be undone.
5)Finally, we commit the overall transaction using the COMMIT statement, which makes the changes permanent. However, since 
we rolled back to the second SAVEPOINT, only the changes up to that point will be committed.
Assignment 6: Draft a brief report on the use of transaction logs for data recovery and create a hypothetical scenario where a
 transaction log is instrumental in data recovery after an unexpected shutdown.
Report: Utilizing Transaction Logs for Data Recovery
Introduction:
Transaction logs play a crucial role in ensuring data integrity and facilitating data recovery in database systems. 
They record all transactions and modifications made to the database, providing a detailed history of changes. In the event of 
unexpected shutdowns, system failures, or data corruption, transaction logs are instrumental in restoring the database to a consistent state.

Purpose of Transaction Logs:
Transaction logs serve multiple purposes in database management:
Data Recovery: Transaction logs enable the recovery of data to a consistent state by replaying transactions from the log, bringing the database back to a point before the failure occurred.
Point-in-Time Recovery: They allow for restoration of the database to a specific point in time, useful for recovering from logical errors or accidental data deletions.
Auditing and Compliance: Transaction logs provide an audit trail, recording all changes to the database, which is essential for compliance with regulatory requirements and forensic investigations.
Replication and Disaster Recovery: Transaction logs facilitate database replication and disaster recovery strategies by enabling the synchronization of data between primary and secondary databases.
Scenario:
Consider a hypothetical scenario where a large e-commerce platform experiences an unexpected system crash during peak shopping hours.
 Orders are being processed, payments are being made, and inventory is being updated when the database server suddenly goes offline due to a power outage.
Impact of Shutdown:
The abrupt shutdown results in the loss of critical transactional data and leaves the database in an inconsistent state. Orders that were in progress 
remain incomplete, payments may have been deducted without proper processing, and inventory levels are uncertain.
Utilizing Transaction Logs for Recovery:
In this scenario, transaction logs become invaluable for restoring the database to a consistent state and recovering lost data. Database administrators leverage transaction logs to:

1)Identify the last committed transactions before the system crash.
2)Replay the transactions from the logs to recreate the database state prior to the crash.
3)Roll back incomplete transactions or reconcile any discrepancies in the data.
4)Perform point-in-time recovery if necessary, to address any erroneous transactions or data modifications that occurred before the crash.
Conclusion:
Transaction logs serve as a vital safety net for data recovery in the event of unexpected shutdowns or failures. By capturing every transaction and change to the
 database, transaction logs enable database administrators to restore data integrity, minimize downtime, and ensure business continuity. Implementing robust backup 
and recovery strategies that incorporate transaction logs is essential for maintaining the reliability and availability of critical systems.


Assignment 6: Create a new database user with specific privileges using the CREATE USER and GRANT commands.
 Then, write a script to REVOKE certain privileges and DROP the user.

1. Create User and Grant Privileges:
-- Create user with username 'app_user' and password 'secure_password' allowing access from localhost
CREATE USER 'app_user'@'localhost' IDENTIFIED BY 'secure_password';

-- Grant SELECT and INSERT privileges on the 'products' database and all its tables
GRANT SELECT, INSERT ON products.* TO 'app_user'@'localhost';

-- Flush privileges to ensure immediate effect
FLUSH PRIVILEGES;
2. Revoke Privileges:
-- Revoke INSERT privilege on the 'products' database
REVOKE INSERT ON products.* FROM 'app_user'@'localhost';
-- User can now only read data (SELECT) but cannot insert new products
3. Drop User:
-- Drop the user 'app_user'
DROP USER 'app_user'@'localhost';
-- User is now removed from the database system
Explanation:
The first part creates the user app_user with a password and allows access from localhost.
Then, it grants SELECT and INSERT privileges on the entire products database for this user.
Flushing privileges ensures the changes take effect immediately.
The second part revokes the INSERT privilege, restricting the user to only reading data.
Finally, the third part permanently removes the user app_user from the database system.
This script demonstrates how to create a user with specific permissions, modify those permissions, and finally 
remove the user entirely. Remember to replace products with your actual database name if needed.



 
